Eldon Pletcher Papers
Eldon Pletcher Papers
1951-1966
1959-1965
Pletcher, Eldon.
18.6 linear ft.
Over 1,500 pieces of original artwork for editorial cartoons drawn for the Sioux City Journal, proofs, correspondence and clippings and reprints. Includes one magazine article in French.
149521
Biographical History
Eldon Pletcher (1922- ) is an American cartoonist best known for his editorial cartoons.
Eldon Pletcher was born in Goshen, Indiana on September 10, 1922 and while in high school, submitted his cartoons to contests. Pletcher studied at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts for a year under cartoonist Vaughn Shoemaker before serving in World War II with the Combat Engineers Battalion. While in the military, Pletcher drew gag cartoons that he submitted to Yank. He also studied at the University of Aberdeen in Scotland and the John Herron Art School in Indianapolis. After getting married, Pletcher moved to Kansas City, Missouri where he worked construction jobs and at an automobile manufacturing plant.
In 1949, Pletcher became the editorial cartoonist for the Sioux City Journal, replacing Roy Justus. Pletcher left Sioux City in 1966 and in December of that year, began drawing cartoons for the New Orleans Times Picayune following Keith Temple's retirement. During the 1970s, Pletcher created First the Good News, a panel cartoon distributed by Rothco Cartoons.
Pletcher was a member of the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists. The Freedoms Foundation honored Pletcher with over a dozen awards, and in 1955, Pletcher won the Christopher Award. Pletcher’s cartoons have appeared in the Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year series and magazines including Time. His work is in the permanent collections of the Harry Truman and Lyndon B. Johnson presidential libraries.
Pletcher retired from the Times Picayune in August 1984.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eldon Pletcher Papers are divided into four series.
Cartoons (1956-1966) contains approximately 1,590 pieces of original artwork for editorial cartoons published in the Sioux City Journal.
There are 1,080 dated cartoons that are arranged chronologically as well as 510 undated cartoons that are arranged alphabetically by caption. Topics of interest are the Cold War and the spread of communism to the western hemisphere, efforts by John F. Kennedy and Dwight Eisenhower to curb economic recessions, the United States’ relationship with Nikita Khrushchev (including his visit to the United States which included a trip to Iowa), the 1960 presidential election, the U-2 incident and pushes for civil rights legislation as far back as 1960. Within Pletcher’s depiction of the 1960 election is the issue of farming, likely reflecting Pletcher’s Midwestern readers. Many cartoons deal with Berlin and the division of East and West Germany.Later cartoons address the United States' increasing involvement in the Vietnam War.
Only a handful of cartoons are Iowa specific. Those that are typically depict the Iowa Legislature and occasionally the Sioux City government.
Original artwork was produced with pen, brush, ink and crayon on paper of varying weights and textures. Traces of blue pencil are visible. This collection reflects changes in Pletcher's style. Early cartoons feature high contrast crayon shading, while cartoons from approximately 1963 onward have zipatone dot screening in addition to shading. Captions appear at the top in ink. Publication dates appear in ink as days of the week and specific dates are also stamped on the front. Artwork measures approximately 15"x 20".
Correspondence (1951-1966) contains primarily incoming correspondence sent to Pletcher or forwarded on to Pletcher by the Sioux City Journal. There is a handful of copies of outgoing carbon responses from Pletcher or at times his editor. Frequently Pletcher’s name is mistaken for Fletcher on the correspondence.
Letters include: those written by political figures including Richard Nixon, Barry Goldwater, Hubert Humphrey and Harry Truman (as well as the director of Truman's presidental library); a thank you note from Jimmy Hoffa; inquiries from magazine and book publishers about reprinting Pletcher’s work and letters from readers including an 83 year old Omaha woman who writes Pletcher several times in the early 1950s. Subjects include opinions on Pletcher’s work, requests for original cartoon artwork and notifications from organizations and awards committees, particularly the Freedoms Foundation. There are also pieces of correspondence from other cartoonists: Dan Dowling, D.R. Fitzpatrick, Scott Long, Jack Bender, Bill Boynansky and Newton Pratt.
Proofs (1958-1966) contains engraver’s proofs of Pletcher's editorial cartoons printed in black and white on glossy paper. Dates are stamped on the top next to captions written in ballpoint pen.
Clippings and Reprints contains several miscellaneous items (some of which are undated), namely clippings of Pletcher's cartoons as they a appeared in magazines such as Time. There is also a magazine article in French with cartoons about international politics, promotional material from the National Newspaper Syndicate and a newspaper clipping about a Freedoms Foundation award and a photograph of an award.
Arrangement of the Collection
Original artwork is arranged chronologically where dates appear and alphabetically by caption where undated. Correspondence and proofs are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also the
Roy Justus Papers
for additional editorial cartoons from the Sioux City Journal.
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A booklet, Albert T. Reid Cartoon Collection: a description and listing of contents has been removed from the collection and sent to Rare Books.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Pletcher, Eldon -- Archives.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Sioux City Journal.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Castro, Fidel, 1926- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; North Atlantic Treaty Organization -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United Nations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress -- Caricatures and cartoons.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Arms race -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Iowa -- Sioux City.; Editorial cartoons -- Iowa -- Sioux City.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Agriculture -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Industrial relations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Communism -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Elections -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Berlin (Germany) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Engraver's proofs.; Editorial cartoons.; Clippings (information artifacts); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eldon Pletcher, 1964-1966.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - Dated, 1,080 items; Click here for a detailed inventory.
    - 1959 Apr, 1959 Sep-Oct, 1960 Jan-May (Oversize 1)
    - 1960 Jun-Nov (Oversize 2)
    - 1960 Dec-1961 Jun (Oversize 3)
    - 1961 Jul-Dec (Oversize 4)
    - 1962 Jan-May (Oversize 5)
    - 1962 Jun-Dec (Oversize 6)
    - 1963 Jan-Jun (Oversize 7)
    - 1963 Jul-Dec (Oversize 8)
    - 1964 Jan-Jun (Oversize 9)
    - 1964 Jul-Dec (Oversize 10)
    - 1965 Jan-Aug (Oversize 11)
    - 1965 Sep-1966 Mar (Oversize 12)
  - Undated
    - A-C, circa 1957-1960; 84 items (Oversize 13)
    - D-G, circa 1956-1960; 67 items (Oversize 14)
    - H-L, circa 1958-1960; 96 items (Oversize 15)
    - M-P, circa 1956-1960; 93 items (Oversize 16)
    - R-Thi, circa 1956-1960; 84 items (Oversize 17)
    - Thr-W, circa 1957-1960; 86 items (Oversize 18)
- Correspondence
  - 1950-1951, 1954-1966, undated (Box 1)
- Proofs
  - circa 1958, 1958 Sep-1960 (Box 2)
  - 1961-1962 Sep, 1962 Nov-1964 (Box 3)
  - 1965, 1966 Jan-Feb (Box 4)
- Clippings and Reprints
  - Freedoms Foundation article and photograph of award, 1956; undated (Box 1)
  - French magazine article with cartoons by various cartoonists, undated; in French (Box 1)
  - National Newspaper Syndicate promotional material, undated (Box 1)
  - Reprints in news magazines, 1958; 1960,; 1963 (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, For example: B1= Box 1.
Acheson, Dean B15
Adams, Sherman B14 B16-B18
Adenauer, Konrad B7-B8
AFL-CIO B4 B18
Africa B2-B3 B9 B13
Alabama B3 B7-B8 B11
Alaska B9
Algeria B1-B3 B5
Alliance for Progress B6-B7
aluminum industry B12
American Medical Association B7 B10
Americans for Democratic Action B10
anti-trust laws B5
Argentina B5 B10
Arkansas (Little Rock) B14-B16 B18
armed forces B5 B10-B12 B18
arts B12
Asia B2 B7-B13 B17
Austria B2
automation B8 B10
Baker, Bobby B8-B11
baker's union B18
Barnett, Ross B6
Beck, Dave B14 B18
Benson, Ezra Taft B1 B3 B15-B16 B18
Berlin B3-B8 B13-B18
Berlin Wall B4-B8 B10-B11
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B10-B12
Britain B3-B4 B7 B10 B12-B13 B15 B18
Brown Sr., Edmund Gerald B6 B13 B16
Brown v. Board of Education B4 B9
budget B1-B3 B5-B8 B12-B13 B15-B17
Bulganin, Nikolai B14
Bulgaria B5
Burch, Dean B10
Burma B3 B9
business B5-B6 B13 B16
Butler, Paul B14 B17
Byrd, Harry B5
California B4-B6 B14
Cambodia B5 B8-B9
Canada B7-B8 B10
capitalism B4 B6 B8 B15
Castro, Fidel B1-B9 B12 B14
census B1
Central Intelligence Agency B3
charity B6 B16
Bowles, Chester B3 B7
Chile B10
Chile, Harold B7
China SEE ALL BOXES
Churchill, Winston B7 B16 B18
civil rights B1-B5 B7-B11 B13 B15-B17
coal industry B7
Cold War SEE ALL BOXES
colonialism B4-B5 B9-B10 B12
common market B4-B8
communications B9
communism B1-B11 B13 B15-B18
Congo B2-B7
Congress SEE ALL BOXES
conservatism B5 B7 B10
copper industry B12
corruption B8 B13 B15-B16 B18
cost of living B13-B18
crime B5 B8 B10-B12
Cuba B1-B4 B6-B10 B12-B15 B18
Cuba Missile Crisis B6
Cyprus B9 B13
Czechoslovakia B5
de Gaulle, Charles B1 B3 B5-B13 B15 B18
Democratic Party SEE ALL BOXES
demonstrations B2 B8 B11-B12
Diem, Ngo Dinh B8
Dirksen, Everett B11-B12
disarmament B1-B4 B6-B7 B10-B11 B13-B15 B18
Dominican Republic B11
drug use B3
drunk driving B6
Dulles, John Foster B1 B13-B14 B18
West New Guinea B5
economy B4-B7 B9 B13-B17
education B3-B4 B16 B18
Egypt B13
Eisenhower, Dwight B1-B3 B6 B8 B10 B12-B18
elections B1-B10 B12-B18
En-lai, Chou B1
Erhard, Ludwig B8 B12
U-2 incident B1-B2 B6
Estes, Billie Sol B5
ethics B3
Europe B7 B10
farming B1-B3 B5 B7 B12 B14-B18
Faubus, Orval B13-B15 B17-B18
Finland B4
Florida B9
Floyd River Valley B1
Ford, Gerald R. B11
foreign aid B1 B3 B5 B7-B9 B11 B14-B17
foreign policy B1 B9-B10 B13 B15-B18
Formosa B13 B15-B16
France B7 B9-B13 B15 B18
free press B6
Freeman, Orville B3 B5 B7
Kozlov, Frol R. B15
gambling B4
Germany B1-B4 B8 B10 B13-B15 B18
Glenn, John B5 B9
gold B2-B3 B8
Goldberg, Arthur B6 B11
Goldwater, Barry B4-B12
government spending B2-B3 B5 B7-B10 B13-B18
graduates B6 B11
Great Society B10-B12
Halleck, Charles B11
Hammarskjold, Dag B2-B3
Harlem B10
health care B1 B5
Herter, Christian B1 B16-B17
Ho Chi Minh B12
Hoffa, Jimmy B1 B3 B9 B13 B15-B18
holidays B2-B4 B6 B8 B10-B14 B16
Hoover Commission B14
housing B9 B11
Humphrey, Hubert B1 B9-B16
Hungary B5 B13 B15-B17
immigration B11
imperialism B2 B5 B8 B11
India B1 B4 B6 B9 B12 B17-B18
Indonesia B8 B11
industry (general) B3 B6 B13
inflation B1 B3 B9 B12 B14-B18
integration B2-B4 B6-B7 B9 B13-B15 B17-B18
Internal Revenue Service B7
Iowa B18
Iowa Legislature B3 B9 B13
Iran B13
Iraq B17-B18
Italy B7
Japan B2
Jim Crow B9 B11
jobs B9
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1 B3-B4 B8-B13 B15-B16 B18
journalism B7 B13 B18
Kaganovich B5
Kai-shek, Chiang B9
Kefauver, Estes B16
Kennedy, Caroline B6
Kennedy, John F. B1-B8 B10 B13 B15-B16
Kennedy, Robert F. B5-B6 B12
Kennedy, Ted B5-B6
Khanh, Nguyen B10
Khrushchev, Nikita B1-B10 B13-B18
Korean War B5 B12 B18
Kosygin, Alexey B11-B12
Ku Klux Klan B11
labor B1 B8 B10 B13-B18
Laos B3-B7 B9 B15 B17
Latin America B1 B3 B5 B7 B9 B12
law and order B11
League of Nations B4
Lebanon B13
Lenin, Vladimir B3 B7
Lincoln, Abraham B9 B11
Lindsay, John B12
Liu, Shaoqi B13
Lodge Jr., Henry Cabot B2 B8-B10
Long, Russell B9
Louisiana B2-B3
MacArthur, Douglas B18
MacMillan, Harold B7-B8 B10 B15 B17
Malaya B5
Malaysia B8-B9 B11
Malenkov, Georgy B5
Malinovsky, Rodion B2
Martin, Joe B15
Marx, Karl B2-B3
McNamara, Robert B7-B12
Meany, George B16 B18
Medicare B5 B7 B10-B11
Meyner, Robert B. B13 B15-B16
Middle East B2 B7 B13-B18
Mikoyan, Anastas B12 B17-B18
minimum wage B3 B12
Mississippi B6 B10
Missouri River B16
Molotov, Vyacheslav B4-B5
Monroe Doctrine B2-B3
Morse, Wayne B1 B16
Morton, Thurston B. B16
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B7 B16 B18
national debt B1 B5 B7-B8 B10 B13-B15 B17-B18
nationalism B13 B15 B18
NATO B1 B6-B12 B14 B18
Nehru, Jawaharlal B1 B4 B6 B16-B17
neutrality B6
New Deal B2
New Frontier B2-B3 B5-B8
New York City B15
Nhu, Madame Ngo Dinh B8
Nixon, Richard M. B1-B10 B12-B15 B17-B18
North Korea B1
nuclear weapons B1-B16 B18
Organization of American States B5
organized crime B2 B4 B8 B13 B15-B18
Pakistan B12
Panama B9 B17
Paraguay B10
Pasternak, Boris B15
payola B1
peace B1-B5 B7-B8 B11-B12 B14-B17
Pentagon B5 B18
Peron, Juan Domingo B5 B10
Poland B5 B17
politics B4-B6 B8 B15
pollution B16
Pope Paul VI B12
population B9 B13
Portugal B4
poverty B9
Profumo Affair B7 B10
propaganda B1-B3 B5-B7 B13 B16-B17
public works B5 B16
Quemoy (Kinmen) and Matsu B2 B6 B16 B18
quiz shows B13 B15 B17
racial violence B3 B8-B11
railroad industry B8 B17
Rayburn, Sam B4 B18
religion B1-B3 B9
Republican Party B1-B3 B5-B18
Reuther, Walter B13 B18
Rhodesia B12
right to work law B12
Rockefeller, Nelson B1-B4 B6-B10 B13-B18
Romania B5
Romney, George W. B6-B9
Roosevelt, Eleanor B2
Rusk, Dean B3 B6 B9 B12
Russia B1-B4 B6 B10 B13-B14 B17-B18
Salinger, Pierre B6 B10
schools B3-B5 B8 B10 B15 B17-B18
Scranton, William B7-B10
SEATO B2
Seaton, Frederick B16
segregation B1 B6-B8 B14-B15 B17
Shao-Chi, Liu B13
Shastri, Lal Bahadur B11
Sioux City, Iowa B1-B2 B8 B16
smoking B9 B11
social security B11 B15
socialism B3
South America B1
South Korea B1
Soviet Union SEE ALL BOXES
space exploration B1-B5 B7 B10-B14 B16-B18
sports B2 B4 B8 B12
Stalin, Joseph B5 B8
Stassen, Harold B7 B9 B16 B18
steel industry B1 B5-B6 B12-B14 B16 B18
Stevenson, Adlai E. B1-B3 B6 B13 B15-B18
stock market B6
strikes B1 B3 B7-B8 B12-B13 B16-B18
Suez Canal B13
Sukarno B5 B8-B9 B11
summer vacation B2 B15
Supreme Court B9
Symington, Stuart B1 B13 B15-B16
taxes B1-B3 B5-B9 B11-B18
Teamsters B14-B18
terrorism B4 B9
Thailand B3 B5 B9
Thant, U. B11
Tibet B13 B15 B17
Tito, Josip Broz B7
trade B4-B5 B8 B14-B15
traffic fatalities B2-B4 B6-B9 B12 B15
transportation B3 B12 B15
Truman, Harry S. B2 B13-B18
U.S. Postal Service B1 B5 B9 B14 B16
Ulbricht, Walter B8
United Auto Workers B16-B17
United Nations B1-B12 B15-B18
University of Alabama B7
University of Mississippi B6
Vietnam B3-B5 B18
Vietnam War B6-B12
Virginia B15 B17
Voroshilov, Kliment B5
voting B1 B9-B11 B16 B18
voting rights B6 B9 B11
Wallace, George B7-B9 B12
Wallace, Lurleen B12
war B12
War on Poverty B9-B11
Warren Commission B10
Washington D.C. (home rule) B12
Washington, George B5
weather B5 B7 B11-B12 B15-B16
Williams, G. Mennen B3 B15
Wilson, Charlie B16
Wilson, Harold B12
World War II B1 B3 B11 B18
Zedong, Mao B1 B3 B7-B13 B17-B18